A Guide to the Jeff Trollinger Papers: Records of the Sexual Minorities Commission and Other Voices Chorus, 1990-2005
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
A Guide to the Jeff Trollinger Papers: Records of the Sexual Minorities Commission and Other Voices Chorus, 1990-2005
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 359
3.4 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in August of 2005 by Mr. Jeff Trollinger.
Custodial History
Virginia Commonwealth University does have a signed Deed of Gift transferring literary property rights.
Biographical Information
Jeff Trollinger is a member of the pastoral care team of St. Michael Catholic Church in Glen Allen, Virginia. Trollinger represents the We are Family portion of the team, which focuses on ministry to Gay and Lesbian Catholics, their families and their friends. He was the vice chair of the Sexual Minorities Commission of the Catholic Church for the years 2000-2002 and the chair of the commission from 2002 until 2004, during which time he collected current events in papers and magazines dealing with gay rights concerns and gay representation in religion. The Commission on Sexual Minorities was the first attempt by a Catholic diocese to reach out to homosexual parishioners when it was established in 1977 in Richmond, Virginia by Bishop Walter Sullivan. While it was not instantly accepted by many in the church, there were more than forty commissions like it twenty years later. It was disbanded in 2004 when Bishop Francis DiLorenzo was appointed to Richmond.
Jeff Trollinger was also a member of Other Voices: The Richmond Lesbian and Gay Chorus, and was made president of the steering committee in 1999.
Scope and Content
The Jeff Trollinger Papers consist of information from the Sexual Minorities Commission including minutes, correspondence, membership files, publications, and a handbook entitled National Association of Catholic Diocesan Lesbian and Gay Ministries (NACDLGM). There is also a large section of papers relating to the Other Voices Chorus. These have minutes, correspondence, membership files, a board member handbook, state incorporation papers, sheet music, and information from the Gay and Lesbian Association (GALA) of Choruses Conference. There is also a videotape. The bulk of the collection consists of original and photocopied scrapbooks kept by Mr. Trollinger that consist of news articles relating to the gay community.
Arrangement
Materials in the collection are in alphabetical order within each series, with the exception of the scrapbooks which are kept in their original order. Photocopies of the scrapbooks are sorted by date.
There are three series in this collection. Series I is the Sexual Minorities Commission, 1975, 1980, 1990-2005, undated. Series II is Other Voices Chorus, 1993-1999, undated. Scrapbooks are series III, dated 1990-2004. Photocopies of the scrapbooks are filed first with originals following. The originals have the complete listing of all headlines.
Contents List
- Sexual Minorities Commission 1975, 1980, 1990-2005 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1975, 1980, 1993-2004, undated (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence 1995-2005, undated (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Membership Files 1990-2004, undated (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Minutes 1993-2004 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - NACDLGM June 2004 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Newsletters undated (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Publications undated (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Retreat Materials 1993-2004 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Other Voices Chorus 1993-1999 (Box 1)
  - Advertising 1997, 1999, undated (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Blank Forms undated (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Board Member Binder 1997 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Board Member Binder 1997 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence 1993-1999, undated (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Finance 1996 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - GALA Choruses Conference Binder undated (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Membership Files 1994,1996-1999, undated (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Minutes 1996-1999 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Miscellaneous Files 1996-1997, undated (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Publications 1997, 1999, undated (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Secretary's Notes undated (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Sheet Music undated (Box-folder 1:21)
  - State Incorporation 1993 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Video and Photo undated (Box-folder 1:23)
- Scrapbooks 1990-2004, undated (Box 1-7)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Scrapbook 1, photocopies 1996-1991 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Scrapbook 2, photocopies 1996-1999 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Scrapbook 3, photocopies 1990-2004 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Scrapbook 3, photocopies 1990-2004 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Scrapbook 3, photocopies 1990-2004 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Scrapbook 1, original 2000-2004, undated. (Box 3)
    - Gay in Roanoke by Cody Lowe, The Roanoke Times, accessed via web 2001 February 1. (Frame 3:1)
    - Family matters by Lisa Applegate, The Roanoke Times, accessed via web 2001 February 1. (Frame 3:2)
    - Telling the World by Mike Hudson and Kathy Lu, The Roanoke Times, 2001 February 1. (Frame 3:3)
    - I'm a loved person by Kathy Lu, The Roanoke Times, 2001 February 1. (Frame 3:4)
    - Everyday People by Mike Hudson, The Roanoke Times, accessed via web 2001 February 6. (Frame 3:5)
    - Looking for Mr. Right by Zeke Barlow, The Roanoke Times, accessed via web 2001 February 6. (Frame 3:6)
    - Keeping a low profile by Mary Bishop, The Roanoke Times, accessed via web 2001 February 6. (Frame 3:7)
    - The Moral Opposition by Cody Lowe, The Roanoke Times, accessed via web 2001 February 6. (Frame 3:8)
    - Blessings and bonds by Mary Bishop, The Roanoke Times, accessed via web 2001 February 6. (Frame 3:9)
    - The Battle for the Soul of the Boy Scouts by David France, Newsweek, 2001 August 6. (Frame 3:10)
    - Acceptance of gays growing, study says, Knight Ridder Newspapers, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2001 November 15. (Frame 3:11)
    - Activist helps gays return to Catholicism by Jennifer Carnig, Oakland Tribune, 2000 September 9 (Frame 3:12)
    - Politicians should leave the Boy Scouts alone by Charley Reese, Oakland Tribune, 2000 September 9 (Frame 3:13)
    - Gay friendly skies, author unknown undated (Frame 3:14)
    - Rabbis likely to back gays from Wire Reports, printed in Richmond Times Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:15)
    - Same-sex prom date allowed, Richmond Times Dispatch, undated (Frame 3:16)
    - Gays Side with Scouts: On the Subtle Distinction between Rights and Freedom by George Will, Washington Post Writer's Group, undated (Frame 3:17)
    - Marlboro Man Yields to a softer kind of guy by Catherine Fitzpatrick, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, undated. (Frame 3:18)
    - Law says sodomy is always illegal: Brief looks to reinforce sodomy law by Lawrence Hammack, The Roanoke Times, undated. (Frame 3:19)
    - Suffering in silence by Bill Plaschke, Los Angeles Times, 2001 January 2. (Frame 3:20)
    - United Methodists pull out of ministry at MWC The Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2001 January 11. (Frame 3:21)
    - Gay group's gifts go unblessed by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2001 January 11. (Frame 3:22)
    - Where Homophobia Does the Most Harm by Judy Mann, Utah Post, 2000 March 1. (Frame 3:23)
    - California Proposition: Referendum on 'Normalcy' by Ellen Goodman, The Boston Globe, undated. (Frame 3:24)
    - Did Column Promote Virtue or Vice? Richmond Times Dispatch, letters to the editor, undated. (Frame 3:25)
    - Gay rights bill clears Vt. House The Associated Press, undated. (Frame 3:26)
    - Tolerant Christians should speak up by Thea Page, Charlottesvilee Daily Progress, 2000 May 1. (Frame 3:27)
    - A Proclamation of Love photo by Juana Arias, The Washington Post, 2000 April 30. (Frame 3:28)
    - Multitudes in D.C. March for gay rights Associated Press, The Daily Progress, 2000 May 1. (Frame 3:29)
    - Mrs. Clinton joins 'inclusive parade' Associated Press, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2000 March 6. (Frame 3:30)
    - Gay fight over parade takes on life of its own Associated Press, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2000 March 6. (Frame 3:31)
    - Scalia stresses traditional values Associated Press,, Hempstead N.Y., undated. (Frame 3:32)
    - Green Party adopts platform Associated Press,, Denver, undated. (Frame 3:33)
    - 100,000 march through Paris in Gay Pride Parade, Paris, undated. (Frame 3:34)
    - Church's Milwaukee synod Oks gay partnerships Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2006 May 4. (Frame 3:35)
    - Protests at meetings of churches Associated Press, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2000 May 21. (Frame 3:36)
    - California Approves Gay Marriage Ban by Bob Egelko, AOL News, The Associated Press, 2000 March 8. (Frame 3:37)
    - Vt. Senate Oks Gay Unions Bill by Ross Sneyd, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 April 19. (Frame 3:38)
    - Court Oks Mandatory Student Fees by Richard Carelli, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 March 22. (Frame 3:39)
    - Reform Rabbis Approve Gay Marriage by Estes Thompson, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 March 29. (Frame 3:40)
    - Episcopal Bishops Disagree on Gays by Leon Drouin Keith, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 April 4. (Frame 3:41)
    - Methodists May Split on Gay Issue by Richard N. Ostling, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 May 2. (Frame 3:42)
    - Miss. Bans Homosexual Adoption by Gina Holland, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 May 3. (Frame 3:43)
    - Vt. Town Rejects Gay Marriage by Mike Eckel, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 March 8. (Frame 3:44)
    - Civil Unions' May Be Disappointing by Ross Sneyd, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 March 17. (Frame 3:45)
    - Canada Board Criticizes Dr. Laura, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 May 11. (Frame 3:46)
    - Methodists Keep Anti-Homosexual Stand by Richard N. Ostling, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 May 11. (Frame 3:47)
    - Church Court Considers Role of Gays by Julia Lieblich, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 May 19. (Frame 3:48)
    - Presbyterians OK Gay 'Holy Unions' by Julia Lieblich, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 May 24. (Frame 3:49)
    - Poll: Americans Back Some Gay Rights by Will Lester, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 May 31. (Frame 3:50)
    - City Council Has Gay Majority by Rachel La Corte, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 June 9. (Frame 3:51)
    - Automakers OK Gay Partner Benefits by Justin Hyde, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 June 8. (Frame 3:52)
    - Sodomy Law Ruled Unconstitutional by Juan A. Lozano, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 June 8. (Frame 3:53)
    - Episcopalians May Sidestep Gay Issue by Judith Kohler, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 July 5. (Frame 3:54)
    - Catholics Drop Interfaith Group Vote, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 June 29. (Frame 3:55)
    - Vt. Gay Couples Joined Legally by Ross Sneyd, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 July 1. (Frame 3:56)
    - Court Says Boy Scouts Can Bar Gays by Laurie Asseo, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 June 28. (Frame 3:57)
    - Episcopal Bishops Nix Gay Rites by Judith Kohler, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 July 12. (Frame 3:58)
    - Episcopalians Move Forward on Gays by Judith Kohler, The Assocaited Press, AOL News, 2000 July 14. (Frame 3:59)
    - High Court: Boy Scouts can bar homosexuals, the Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2000 June 29. (Frame 3:60)
    - Sodomy appeals hit court by Laurence Hammack, The Roanoke Times, 2000 June 29. (Frame 3:61)
    - New thrift store gives away profits by Elana Simms, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2000 August 6 (Frame 3:62)
    - Aging brings new issues by Marsha King, The Seattle Times, 2001 October 21. (Frame 3:63)
    - Bishop Sullivan recognized for forming, sustaining pioneering ministry to gays, Catholic Virginian, 2001 October 1. (Frame 3:64)
    - Gay marriages rise Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2001 December 13. (Frame 3:65)
    - Presbyterians revisiting gay ordination issue by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 February 8. (Frame 3:66)
    - Bill would limit discussion of gays by Paige Akin, Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:67)
    - Gay adoption wins backing The Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:68)
    - Gay priest ignites debate The Associated Press, 2002 February 10. (Frame 3:69)
    - Readers Debate Homosexual Adoption-letters to the editor, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 March 6. (Frame 3:70)
    - Gay travel industry growing by Daniel Barrick, New York Times News Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 May 5. (Frame 3:71)
    - Gays in School by Paige Akin, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 March 5. (Frame 3:72)
    - ROSMY a haven of support by Paige Akin, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 March 5. (Frame 3:73)
    - A Church Crisis of Potentially Epidemic Proportions... by Ross Mackenzie, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 March 28. (Frame 3:74)
    - ...Is it Finally Time for a Public Reckoning? by Maureen Dowd, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 March 28. (Frame 3:75)
    - How I became a foster parent by Rosie O'Donnell, rosie, by Rosie O'Donnell, Volume CXXI Number 6, 2002 April. (Frame 3:76)
    - Love vs. the law by Jane Meredith Adams, rosie, by Rosie O'Donnell, Volume CXXIX Number 6, 2002 April. (Frame 3:77)
    - Presbyterian leader says he'll confront gay issue by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 April 13. (Frame 3:78)
    - Priests Concerned about Gay Subcultures, undated (Frame 3:79)
    - TV topic: Roanoke's attitude toward gays by Rex Bowman, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 May 23. (Frame 3:80)
    - Roanoke on TV: gays and religion by Rex Bowman, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 May 26. (Frame 3:81)
    - Insufficient evidence keeps openly gay Methodist in Wash. pulpit The Associated Press, printed in The Roanoke Times, 2002 June 1. (Frame 3:82)
    - Bill gives benefits to same-sex couples Los Angeles Times and Washington Post Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 June 26. (Frame 3:83)
    - Bishop backs gays in church by Mark Holmberg, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 October 12. (Frame 3:84)
    - Pride comes out at festival by Paige Akin, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 September 16. (Frame 3:85)
    - Presbyterians back ban on ordaining active gays by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:86)
    - 1 Family, 2 Dads by Paige Akin, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 July 2. (Frame 3:87)
    - Court to revisit 2 Powell sing-vote cases by Linda Greenhouse, New York Times News Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2002 December 4. (Frame 3:88)
    - Supreme Court weighs challenge to Texas' homosexual sodomy law, The New York Times, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 March (Frame 3:89)
    - Gay bookstores fall on lean times by Larry Fish, Knight Ridder Newspapers, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 January 26. (Frame 3:90)
    - The Military's Closet by Paige Akin, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 February 5. (Frame 3:91)
    - Lawyers argue for gay rights Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 March 27. (Frame 3:92)
    - Behind private doors... by David G. Savage, Los Angeles Times and Washington Post Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 March 26. (Frame 3:93)
    - Canada to allow gay marriage Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 June. (Frame 3:94)
    - SBC initiative reaches out to gays Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 June. (Frame 3:95)
    - Scout council may lose more funding Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 June 26. (Frame 3:96)
    - Gay marriage at issue Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 June 22. (Frame 3:97)
    - Richmond Times-Dispatch Section A, 2003 June 27 (Frame 3:98)
    - Justices void gay-sex ban, Ruling invalidates laws in Texas, 12 other states New York News Service, Assembly resisted efforts to repeal Virginia statue by Jeff E. Shapiro and Alan Cooper, undated. (Frame 3:99)
    - Ruling may spark fight over gay marriage by David Von Drehle, Los Angeles Times and Washington Post News Service, undated. (Frame 3:100)
    - Scalia rips decision The Associated Press, undated. (Frame 3:101)
    - Decision produces gratitude, despair The Associated Press, 2003 June. (Frame 3:102)
    - Court took moderate turn by Charles Lane, Los Angeles Times and Washington Post News Service, 2003 June 29. (Frame 3:103)
    - Gay pride parades celebrate ruling The Associated Press, 2003 June 30. (Frame 3:104)
    - Frist backs gay-marriage ban The Associated Press, 2003 June 30. (Frame 3:105)
    - Wal-Mart to protect gay employees New York Times News Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July 2. (Frame 3:106)
    - Reactions to Supremes' Rulings Miss the Mark by A. Barton Hinkle, undated. (Frame 3:107)
    - Court Just Slammed Nation's Bedroom Door by William Safire, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July 1. (Frame 3:108)
    - Opening the door Richmond Times-Dispatch, Virginia News Leader, 2003 July 2. (Frame 3:109)
    - Presbyterian church invites gays, lesbians by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:110)
    - Case Was More about Privacy than Due Process by William Buckley, Universal Press Syndicate, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July. (Frame 3:111)
    - Court Usurped States' Legislative Role by Bob Marshall, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July. (Frame 3:112)
    - Ohio minister ousted Associated Press Reports, undated. (Frame 3:113)
    - Supreme Court Goes Around the Bend on Diversity, Sodomy by Mark Steyn, 2003 July. (Frame 3:114)
    - Constitution Seems to Be Whatever Justice O'Connor Says It Is by Charles Krauthammer, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July. (Frame 3:115)
    - Sodomy ruling might not alter much in Va. by Laurence Hammack, The Roanoke Times, 2003 July 6. (Frame 3:116)
    - 'Progressives' Push to Keep Current with Culture by George Will, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July. (Frame 3:117)
    - Panel: Strike sodomy statues by Tyler Whitley, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July 17. (Frame 3:118)
    - Ruling Prompts Responses [Texas Case] Richmond Times-Dispatch, letters to the editor, 2003 July. (Frame 3:119)
    - Gay marriage debate begins to heat up across country The New York Times printed in The Roanoke Times, 2003 July 6. (Frame 3:120)
    - Bush opposes gay unions The Associated Press printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July. (Frame 3:121)
    - Additional Letters to the Editor, Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:122)
    - Appointing Justices for all, Horizon section, The Roanoke Times, 2003 July 6. (Frame 3:123)
    - Ideological nominations are injudicious trend by Anthony Lewis, undated. (Frame 3:124)
    - Politics and court appointments go hand in hand by Peter Irons, undated. (Frame 3:125)
    - Alas, the affirmative action decisions clarified nothing by Steven Lubet, undated. (Frame 3:126)
    - Bp. Gregory deplores ruling of high court on sodomy laws The Catholic Virginian, 2003 July 7. (Frame 3:127)
    - Gay choir director's firing brings rift in Ill. Catholic congregation the Associated Press, printed in The Roanoke Times, 2003 July 6. (Frame 3:128)
    - Ottowa bishop will suspend priests who perform same-sex marriages by Art Babych, Catholic News Service, printed in The Catholic Virginian, 2003 July 7. (Frame 3:129)
    - Being gay and married? the Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:130)
    - More gay men, women choosing to be parents by Jane Brody, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July. (Frame 3:131)
    - Op/Ed Section Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July 5. (Frame 3:132)
    - What Do Canadians think? by William Buckley, Universal Press Studios, undated. (Frame 3:133)
    - In Texas Case, Court Corrected Manifest Injustice by Molly Ivins, Creators Syndicate, undated. (Frame 3:134)
    - O'Connor Opinion Was Right On by Paul Greenberg, Tribune Media Services, undated. (Frame 3:135)
    - Why Do You Oppose Gay Marriage? by Leonard Pitts, Tribune Media Services, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August 6. (Frame 3:136)
    - Approval of gay bishop finalized from Wire Reports, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August 6. (Frame 3:137)
    - Allen holds off on gay-marriage ban by Peter Hardin, Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:138)
    - Washington Correspondent, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July (Frame 3:139)
    - Vatican condemns gay marriages New York News Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August 1. (Frame 3:140)
    - Gay marriage drive encounters backlash by David Crary, The Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August 1. (Frame 3:141)
    - Robinson's accuser regrets using 'harassment' The Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August 6. (Frame 3:142)
    - Same-sex policy left to pastors Los Angeles Times and Washington Poste News Service, 2003 August 7. (Frame 3:143)
    - Virginia diocese policy bars gay bishop by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times-Dispatch 2003 August 7. (Frame 3:144)
    - Gay cleric wins first vote The Associated Press, 2003 August. (Frame 3:145)
    - Policy on same-sex blessing passes New York News Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, undated. (Frame 3:146)
    - Morality and the Law by Mark Rush, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 July 9. (Frame 3:147)
    - Anglican leader calls rare summit New York News Service, 2003 August 9. (Frame 3:148)
    - Episcopalians' split easier said than done by Deborah Caldwell, New York News Service, printed in Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August 10. (Frame 3:149)
    - Lutherans debate same-sex marriages The Associated Press, 2003 August 10. (Frame 3:150)
    - How Oppose 'Full Faith and Credit'? by William Buckley, Universal Press Syndicate, undated. (Frame 3:151)
    - Did the Church Do the Right Thing? letts to the editor, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August. (Frame 3:152)
    - Suddenly, Canada is no longer dull by Ron C. Judd, The Seattle Times, 2003 August 10. (Frame 3:153)
    - Church's Okay Boosts Gays by Mark Steyn, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 2003 August. (Frame 3:154)
    - Episcopal groups halt donations The Associated Press, 2003 August 23. (Frame 3:155)
    - A Public School for Gays? There's a Better Way by Leonard Pitts, Tribune Media Services, printed in Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 August. (Frame 3:156)
    - Cartoon For Better or Worse by Lynn Johnston, 2003 August. (Frame 3:157)
    - On the outs: Gay youths struggle for acceptance by Melinda Rogers, Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 August 17. (Frame 3:158)
    - It's the summer of guys and gays by Frazier Moore, The Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 August 16. (Frame 3:159)
    - Readers Debate Homosexuality, Church letters to the editor, Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 August 16. (Frame 3:160)
    - Bush grapples with gay rights by Ron Hutcheson, Knight Ridder Newspapers, printed in Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 August 31. (Frame 3:161)
    - Majority against gay marriages, poll says The Associated Press, printed in Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 August 16. (Frame 3:162)
    - Gays blend with straights by Kate Zernike, Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 August 24. (Frame 3:163)
    - At the threshold by Cody Lowe, The Roanoke Times, 2003 September 7. (Frame 3:164)
    - Understanding the biblical view of homosexuality by Gerald R. McDermott, The Roanoke Times, 2003 October 12. (Frame 3:165)
    - Virginia bishop stays with church by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 October 15. (Frame 3:166)
    - Document rebukes church on gay issue The Associated Press, undated. (Frame 3:167)
    - Gay couples seek equality by Alberta Lindsey, Richmond Times Dispatch, 2003 October 15. (Frame 3:168)